Guide to the Records of the A/P/A Voices A COVID-19 Public Memory Project TAM.837
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Rongkilyo, Set Hernandez, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_67
  Set Hernandez Rongkilyo is a filmmaker, cultural worker, and community organizer. Rongkilyo is an undocumented immigrant who originates from Bicol, Philippines. Rongkilyo produces videos and short documentaries that advance grassroots messaging for migrant justice campaigns. Their work is rooted in the belief that cultural strategies can propel political transformation, and to do this, directly-impacted people must embrace the empowerment to tell their own stories authentically. Since 2010, Rongkilyo has been involved in organizing efforts around migrant justice issues such as education equity for undocumented students, deportation defense, driver's licenses, and healthcare access for undocumented Californians. Rongkilyo's short films have been televised, featured, and awarded in film festivals across the U.S. Their current film projects explore the intersectional issues impacting undocumented immigrants, including the connection between immigrant rights and disability rights.
  Rongkilyo was also the Assistant Editor and Impact Producer for PJ Raval's award-winning documentary, Call Her Ganda, which premiered at the 2018 Tribeca Film Festival. Rongkilyo's 2019 short documentary, COVER/AGE, follows the campaign to expand healthcare access for undocumented elderly immigrants in California by centering the voices of immigrant health justice leaders. In addition to the 2018 Firelight Media Impact Producer Fellowship, Rongkilyo is the recipient of the 2019 Working Docs in Action Film Fund, 2019 Annenberg Civic Media Fellowship, 2017 Soros Justice Fellowship, among others. Rongkilyo co-founded the UndocuFilmmakers Collective, a space for undocumented filmmakers situated across the United States.
- Samuelu, Tavae, 2020
  - Digital Files, TW_TAM_837_ER_68
    Materials include a transcript from an oral history interview conducted by Crystal (Mun-Hye) Balk on November 22, 2020. In her interview, Tavae Samuelu discusses the impact of COVID-19 on her national organizing work with EPIC (Empowering Pacific Islander Communities), as well as on her multigenerational family in Long Beach, CA. Samuelu discusses the specific impact COVID-19 has had on Native Hawaiian Pacific Islander (NHPI) communities and how these communities have been disproportionately impacted by COVID-19. She emphasizes that everyone across NHPI communities are only a degree removed from knowing someone who has passed away from the virus. In her interview, Samuelu discusses the entrenched politics of disposability and dispossession that shape NHPI communities' experiences, in regards to their limited access to resources and the lack of ethical response from political leaders in the United States.
    Throughout the interview, Samuelu makes clear that COVID-19 has only made hyper-visible the fracture points and existing inequities that already exist in U.S. settler society; and the ways that Indigenous peoples, including Samoan and other Pacific Islander communities, have for centuries survived multiple catastrophes. Samuelu shares how she and her household contracted COVID-19 over the summer of 2020 and the anxieties, fears, and concerns related to becoming sick again and impacting others. Samuelu mentions the struggles she and other NHPI leaders and organizations face as their communities have collapsed with Asian Americans and the tokenization that often happens with her leadership in Asian American institutional spaces. She ends the interview by discussing how COVID-19 has impacted her own perspectives regarding her own body, health, and the comfort provided by rest and naps.
    Tavae Samuelu is the daughter of a pastor from Leulumoega and a nurse from Saleimoa in Sāmoa. Tavae was born in Compton, CA; raised in Long Beach, CA; and credits the Bay Area for her political identity and consciousness. Of the many titles she has, the most important one is Aunty Vae.
- Sridaran, Lakshmi, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_69
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Amita Manghnani on August 24, 2021. During her interview, Lakshmi Sridaran talks about her work as Executive Director of South Asian Americans Leading Together (SAALT) and describes some of the specific ways South Asian communities in the U.S. have been impacted by the COVID-19 pandemic. Sridaran draws attention to the disparities and inequities within these communities, pointing out that working class and minority South Asians, including Muslims and Sikhs, have been more impacted by the failure of the state and social injustice of the last 16+ months. She also discusses SAALT's responses to its constituents and member organizations, which comprise the National Coalition of South Asian Organization, many of whom were reporting issues accessing health care, hospital beds, food, domestic violence resources, legal services, employment, benefits, assistance, and information about COVID-19 in South Asian languages.
  Sridaran points out that as the federal government failed to adequately respond and nonprofits were stretched so thin, SAALT shifted its focus from policy advocacy to on-the-ground response. She also shares her personal experience of being pregnant and becoming a parent during the pandemic; coping with her father being sick and in the hospital; and her visions for a "post-pandemic" world. Sridaran reflects on the impact the Black Lives Matter (BLM) movement has had on her development as an organizer; the evolving public discourse on the occupation of Palestine; the very recent events surrounding American withdrawal from Afghanistan; and the approaching twentieth anniversary of September 11 and its significance in today's discourse on anti-Asian racism.
  Lakshmi Sridaran is the Executive Director of South Asian Americans Leading Together (SAALT). Since 2014, she was SAALT's Director of National Policy and Advocacy, where she led the organization's external engagement and developed SAALT's policy and legislative agenda, which primarily focuses on immigration, racial profiling, and combating hate violence. Prior to that, she served as the Policy Director for The Praxis Project, a Washington D.C. based national movement support organization focused on health justice in communities of color. Before moving to D.C., Sridaran completed six years of work in New Orleans, LA after Hurricane Katrina, helping improve federal contracting opportunities for Disadvantaged Business Enterprises; instituting participatory budgeting; and preserving public schools and infrastructure. Sridaran holds a M.A. in City Planning from Massachusetts Institute of Technology and a B.A. in Ethnic Studies from The University of California, Berkeley.
- Su, Celina, 2020-2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_70
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Diane Wong on September 3, 2021. A flyer for Celina Su's playground reading event and two articles written by Su are also included.
  The interview starts with Su sharing her experiences of the COVID-19 lockdown, the rush of emotions when her partner was sick, and the logistics of trying to care for her father in Queens. Su also talks about the various hardships of new motherhood, especially the lack of support from the state during the pandemic; and the community of support she found elsewhere through mutual aid and other localized networks. Su talks about an outdoor playground reading she organized in a park that brought together mothers and children in the neighborhood. In the second half of the interview, Su shares an excerpt from correspondence she wrote with her friend Wah-Ming that was published in the Brooklyn Rail about experiences of sheltering in place during the pandemic. The conversation ends with Su talking about her fears for the current state of the world and hopes for an abundant future.
  Celina Su was born in São Paulo, Brazil and as of 2020, lives in Brooklyn, NY. She is a poet and writer; and the Marilyn J. Gittel Chair in Urban Studies and professor of Political Science at the City University of New York. She has written several books including Landia and Streetwise for Booksmarts: Grassroots Organizing and Education Reform in the Bronx; and has had pieces featured in the New York Times Magazine, Harper's, and n+1. Su's work focuses on everyday struggles for collective governance, centered economic justice, and racial justice. She is also the co-founder of Kwah Dao, the Burmese Refugee Project, which was founded in 2000. Su served as the Executive Director and then a board member until 2016.
- Sunwoo, Elizbeth "Liz", 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_71
  Materials include a transcript and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Crystal (Mun-Hye) Balk on August 13, 2020. In her interview, Elizabeth "Liz" Sunwoo discusses what it has been like to live in a COVID-19 epicenter, Los Angeles, CA; and the challenges COVID-19 has created for her family and the organizations she works with as a social justice consultant. She discusses the intersection of COVID-19 and racial justice; shares what it has been like to raise two young daughters in Koreatown; and recognizes the ways in which racial, class, and gender privilege impact the everyday decisions she makes personally and professionally. Sunwoo discusses the formation of Kids for Justice and Freedom, an experimental network modeled on the Radical Monarchs that provides a critical experiential learning space where young children aged 8-12 learn about and tackle racial, gender, sexual, and class asymmetries, while also providing children the opportunity to inhabit decision-making positions. Finally, Sunwoo discusses the impact COVID-19 and racial violence has had on the organizations she works with, including youth-based organizations that focus on homeless populations in Los Angeles County.
  Elizabeth "Liz" Sunwoo is a social justice movement and organizing consultant based in Los Angeles, CA. She has a long history of working with immigrant justice, labor rights, and multiracial solidarity organizations; and collaboratives, including what was then called the Korean Immigrant Workers Alliance (KIWA) and the Multi-ethnic Immigrant Worker Organizing Network (MIWON). She also worked as the Southern California Organizing Director for Change to Win Labor Federation; and the Director of Leadership Development and Civic Engagement at CDTech in South Los Angeles.
  For the last several years, Sunwoo has been working as a social justice consultant working on initiatives with the Department of Child and Family Services in Los Angeles County; the California Endowment's Building Healthy Communities South Los Angeles site; the CA Labor Commissioner's Office; the James Irvine Foundation's Worker Influence Initiative and Dignity in Schools California that aims to use research and organizing to end the School to Prison pipeline; and most recently, the UCLA Asian American Labor Studies Center.
- Svetvilas, Chanika, 2020-2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_72
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from two oral history interviews conducted by Tomie Arai on July 7, 2020 and January 26, 2021. The film COVID-19 Chapters 1 & 2, which is also included, was filmed and edited by Svetvilas and documents her experience during COVID-19.
  In her July 7, 2020 interview, Chanika Svetvilas discusses the impact the pandemic had on her family – both her sisters are nurses. Svetvilas talk about producing and sewing protective gowns and PPE for essential workers during the early stages of the pandemic and her work as an advocate for disability justice. In her work in disability justice, Svetvilas comments on how moving online has made many events more accessible. She emphasizes that accessibility and inclusion like this should not be afterthoughts or products of necessity, but instead part of everyday life. Svetvilas also talks about disability as a spectrum and oftentimes being invisible, like in the case of her bipolar disorder. Svetvilas reflects on the possibility of returning to "normal," but reaffirms that normal is a standard that is problematic and does not really exist. Svetvilas contextualizes this in how a return to normal would negatively impact the disability community.
  In her January 26, 2021 interview, Svetvilas discloses she has received a rent grant lottery from New Jersey and has had two-thirds of her rent covered for six months. She goes on to discuss the ways her family continues to be affected by the pandemic, especially due to the fact that most of them are essential workers. Svetvilas touches on how she has kept in remote contact with her father in Thailand and siblings throughout the U.S. via online chatting and family video calls.
  Chanika Svetvilas is a Thai-American interdisciplinary artist and disability rights activist. She has presented her work at Stony Brook University, the Queens Museum, ABC No Rio, the Brooklyn Public Library, and other spaces. In 2020, she curated Unique Minds: Creative Voices, an exhibition of art and creative writing for Princeton University's Mental Health Awareness Month. She is the co-founder of ThaiLinks, a collective that was based in New York City dedicated to increasing awareness about Thai issues and the Thai American community; and Thai Takes, a biennial Thai film festival presented in New York City.
  After experiencing a bipolar manic episode and hospitalization in 2010, Svetvilas was motivated to explore her experience and to break the stigma connected to invisible disabilities. She decided to use her art practice to create safe spaces that build community through public interactions. As a mental health advocate, Svetvilas has presented at national mental health conferences on arts and disability and addresses her personal experiences with discrimination and stigma.
- Taiko Community Alliance, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_73
  Materials include a video of "Taiko and COVID-19: Sharing Experiences," which captures commentary from leaders within the taiko community, sharing how COVID-19 has impacted them and their taiko.
  The Taiko Community Alliance (TCA) is a 501(c)3 nonprofit organization with a mission to empower the people and advance the art of taiko, or Japanese drumming. TCA was the first nonprofit outside of Japan to provide art services and resources to taiko practitioners.
- Tirona, Marissa, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_74
  Materials include a transcript from an oral history interview conducted by Lena Sze on March 7, 2021. In her interview, Marissa Tirona recounts her experiences during the early days of New York City's location as a global epicenter in March 2020; her hospitalization as a result of COVID-19 that included a 28-day induced coma during which she was on life support; the remainder of her stay at the hospital and a rehabilitation center into May 2020; and her recovering and healing process since her hospitalization. Tirona discusses her frightening ordeal, and the intensity and trauma of her family's experience, particularly her teenage daughter, Bebe, and her husband, Ephraim. She reflects on the connections with her community; and how she understands care and caregiving, especially on the part of her husband. As a social justice advocate active in philanthropy, Tirona spends time reflecting on the meaning and experience of the Black Lives Matter (BLM) protests of 2020; and the intertwined and complicated politics around anti-Asian violence during the pandemic. She speaks of these larger political movements in terms of her own experience, especially as she watches her child develop her own analysis and consciousness as a mixed-race person, Filipina/Black/White, growing up during this pandemic.
  Marissa Tirona is a Filipino American woman who lives and works in New York City.
- Vaj, Kabzuag, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_75
  Materials include a transcript and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Crystal (Mun-Hye) Balk on July, 10, 2020. In her interview, Kabzuag Vaj describes how Freedom Inc.'s work in Madison, WI centers on the critical health, wellbeing, and power of Black, Southeast Asian, and refugee communities. She describes the pre-pandemic structural violence experienced by Black and Southeast Asian peoples; and how these precarities have only been amplified by COVID-19. Vaj also describes the origins of Freedom Inc. prior to 2003 and how influential her experiences abroad helped conceptualize the organization, especially in regards to her experiences in Thai refugee camps. Through these experiences, Vaj questioned why and how certain peoples and communities experienced uneven levels of state violence, socioeconomic precarity, and loss -- a line of questioning that brought her to a more developed critique of racial capitalism.
  At the beginning of the pandemic, Vaj describes the fear and anxieties experienced by Southeast Asian and Black communities, particularly among elders. She describes the difficulties experienced by youths who could not access the Internet for school and the domestic violence others were experiencing in their homes. As a consequence of the pandemic, Freedom Inc. had to shift its work foci by supporting mutual aid, housing access, food access, direct service, and support; while also supporting Black Lives Matter organizing, racial justice, and liberation. Vaj mentions the anti-Asian sentiments and anti-Blackness she's experienced within her own community, and how supporting Black Lives Matter is crucial given that Black liberation lifts and supports our entire society and social ecosystem. In the context of George Floyd's murder in May 2020 in Minneapolis, Vaj emphasizes the urgent necessity of framing the protests as an uprising for justice within the Southeast Asian community, rather than describing it as "looting" or "property damage." Lastly, Vaj emphasizes that because of the violence and urgency of the current moment, there has been no moment to rest for community organizers such as herself, who are also essential workers.
  Kabzuag Vaj was born in Laos and came to the United States as a refugee with her mother and siblings. She is the founder and co-executive director of Freedom Inc., a Black and Southeast Asian nonprofit organization that works with low to no-income communities of color. Vaj has dedicated the majority of her life to ending gender-based violence. Her advocacy started when she was 16 years old, assisting and housing at-risk teens; and challenging abusive gender norms within her community. She is a strong believer that those who are most deeply impacted must be at the forefront of the movement and have opportunities and resources to advocate for themselves and tell their own stories.
  Vaj has spent her life working to build collective power and social change within Southeast Asian and Black communities. She was recognized as a Champion of Change at the White House during Domestic Violence Awareness month in 2011 and was named one of "20 Women of Color in Politics to Watch in 2020" by She the People. Vaj is a co-founder of Building Our Future, a global community campaign that works to change traditional practices, behaviors, and beliefs that contribute to gender-based violence within Hmong Families while building the leadership of women and girls. Vaj is also a co-owner and founder of Red Green Rivers, a social enterprise that works with artisan makers, most of whom are women and girls, from the Mekong Region in Southeast Asia. Vaj is a daughter, mother, artist, and organizer.
- Vani, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_76
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Lena Sze on August 7, 2020. In this interview, Vani discusses aspects of this pandemic ranging from workplace policies and their partial furlough; the profit-driven model of higher education as evidenced through this pandemic; forms of community built geographically through a mutual aid group in a very gentrified Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood they were involved in; and socializing virtually through a book club that was important to them during the pandemic. Vani discusses the grief of losing people to COVID-19; and discusses the protests and politics following the murder of George Floyd, racial justice, trans rights, abolitionism, anti-Islamophobia, and Hindu nationalism.
  Biographical / Historical
  Vani is an Indian American writer and librarian living in New York City.
- Wang, Claire, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_78
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Sarah Lin on July 30, 2020. In the interview, Claire Wang discusses her journalistic work and reflects on how topics she focused on changed over the course of the pandemic. Some COVID-19 related topics Wang covered include a story about Korean BBQ restaurants affected by COVID-19; and attempting to locate the intersection between the anti-Asian xenophobia, the economic downturn, and racial justice protests. During the course of her reporting, Wang realized an under coverage of Asian American stories in media and journalism. As the pandemic continued, Wang's stories evolved to include stories about Asian American restaurants and seniors; and as summer 2020 continued, she began to cover Asian Americans and the Black Lives Matter movement. Wang's work during the pandemic made her realize the challenges of being a journalist in an online/remote environment and the need for self-care. She also learned some systemic challenges moving forward and the importance of creating a public memory.
  Claire Wang is a California-based freelance reporter who writes about politics, culture, and Asian-American issues. Her byline has appeared in NBC News, Atlas Obscura, Mic, Vice, the South China Morning Post, the American Prospect, and several other publications.
- Williams, Kai Naima, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_79
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on December 1, 2021. In the interview Kai Naima Williams recounts being a senior at Wesleyan University and being on Spring Break with her friends in California when the COVID-19 lockdowns began. She remembers finishing her last semester virtually and thinking she and her friends would return to campus to graduate together, but was disappointed when they did not return and she was unable to experience a traditional graduation ceremony.
  Williams recounts attending Black Lives Matter (BLM) protests in high school and compares how different it was during the pandemic. In 2020, she wanted to attend as many BLM protests as possible, but was afraid of contracting COVID-19 at the marches and then potentially spreading it to her family. As a Black multiracial woman with Black family members, Williams describes how painful it is to see Black people continuously murdered in this country and how difficult it was to not have the same in-person support structures in place because of the pandemic.
  Williams talks about her paternal great-grandmother, Yuri Kochiyama, a radical activist and freedom fighter who fought for all oppressed people in this country. For Williams, Kochiyama has become a symbol of solidarity, particularly for her work in combating anti-Black racism. Being both Black and Asian, Williams was troubled by the tensions between the Black and Asian communities, especially during a time of increased violence against both communities. When the Atlanta spa shootings happened and six Asian women were murdered, Williams experienced a similar depression to when George Floyd was killed, however, this time she felt more isolated in her grief due to her lack of Asian friends.